Hey everyone and thanks for jumping back
into the cryptoverse.
Today, we're going to talk about Bitcoin
between a rock and a hard place. If you
guys like the content, make sure you
subscribe to the channel, give the video
a thumbs up, and also check out the sale
on Into the Cryptoverse Premium at
intothecryptoverse.com.
As a reminder, the ITC conference will
be in late November, November 20th
through the 22nd. So, make sure you guys
get your ticket if you have not already
done so. We're still
curating the list of speakers. We've
already got a lot of great speakers
coming, and we hope to get even more.
So, let's go ahead and jump in. What I
We've talked about this before, but the
the reality is that Bitcoin is
essentially trading between two very key
levels that it seems to not get a
durable move past.
One of which, of course, as you guys
know, is the bear market resistance
band.
Bitcoin continues to get rejected by it
to the upside,
but to the downside, it's the 200-week
moving average.
And what you'll notice
is that the first time we approached the
bear market resistance band,
we barely got to it.
The first time we approached the
200-week moving average, we didn't even
get all the way there.
The second time we approached the bull
market support band or the bear market
resistance band, we got through it. We
had a fake out above it.
The second time we approached the
200-week moving average,
we actually got below it. Again, a fake
out.
So, what's happening for Bitcoin right
now is that it's ping-ponging between
the 200-week moving average and the bear
market resistance band. Now, what's
fascinating
is that this is all lining up with the
four-year cycle, right? It all It all
lines up fairly well in the sense of how
the markets tend to play out. We
normally get lows in like late June,
early July, as you can see in
the summer of '22, the summer of '2018.
Sorry, that's February '2018, the summer
of '2018. And you'll notice that after
Bitcoin gets down there, to say sweeping
a prior low or even going lower, it then
bounces back up in July.
And if you look at monthly returns
for Bitcoin
in midterm years,
you'll see that in 2026, so far
Bitcoin's up about 9%. In 2022, it was
up 20. In 2018, it was up almost 40.
Now, in 2014, it was slightly negative.
So, it's not to say that it can't be
negative, but usually in midterm years,
July isn't
as bad of a month as the months that
surround it. Look at May and June in
midterm years. This year, it was -3.5%
and -20%.
In 2022, it was -17% and -38%.
2018 was -21% and -20%. And then 2014,
we actually had a positive May
and only a slightly red June, but then
all the red you know, still eventually
came and we we did go lower.
If you look on the other side of July,
right? The other side of it. Look at
2022. After a green July, August and
September were red. In 2018, after a
green July, August and September were
red. And in 2014, July was red and then
August and September were also red. So,
when you think about like how this could
play out,
I think that the time frame for Bitcoin
to to stay strong will be ending within
two to two to four weeks. You have this
brief window of weakness that opens
after the summer low,
late June, early July. After that low,
it opens up, it allows Bitcoin to head
higher, but as we get into that August,
September time frame, we're probably
going to give back those gains. Just
like in 2022, we rallied in July and
gave back those gains into August and
September. The rally did last through
early August. We didn't really get the
correction until about mid-August. In
2022, or sorry, 2018, the correction
actually started in late July. But, the
point is is the gains that we had in
July were given back
in the August to September time frame.
So, if we were to just kind of extend
this out, the bear market resistance
band and the 200-week moving average,
you're essentially looking at a scenario
here where Bitcoin keeps bouncing back
and forth between them until it's forced
to make a decision.
And what I'm saying
is that if the four-year cycle were to
remain intact in the sense of like the
the the seasonal weakness that we
normally see, the expectation, although
it doesn't have to play out like this,
but the the the baseline expectation, I
would assume, would be that it actually
breaks down a little bit later on. It
breaks down
and then from that level, it'd be And
and it breaks down around the time that
the stock market gets a 10 to 20% drop.
That's what we saw in 2014, 2018, and
2022. And then from that breakdown,
you form the market cycle bottom, and
then we go into the next bull market.
If we don't break down by the end of the
year, then I would probably have to
pivot that view and say, "All right,
look, we had the time to go lower, and
it just didn't happen. And and and now
it's time to pivot. There's nothing
wrong with pivoting." And I even told
you guys that back over here. I was
like, "I don't think February is the
low,
but even if it's not the low, we're
going to come back down and retest it in
the summer, like we normally do.
So,
it's hard to say for sure about 57k. I
mean, some of the on-chain indicators
have now triggered, but still a lot
haven't.
I would say I would think we're going to
at least retest it, probably go a little
bit lower later in the year to fully
reset the on-chain indicators, but if we
haven't done that by the end of the
year, then I would defer to the
time-based capitulation and say, "All
right, the bull market's back at that
point." But, that's not where we are
right now, right? We're in the period
of bouncing back and forth between these
two levels because there hasn't really
been a great reason to durably go up
when you have, you know, this midterm
year weak seasonality, but also there
hasn't been the catalyst necessarily to
take us down, especially considering
that the S&P hasn't really entered into
that correction yet, right? The
correction that Bitcoin had when it
bottomed out in February sort of
preceded this larger drop in stocks. We
haven't had that yet. And if you guys
remember what I said was expect a small
drop a small drop a shallow drop by the
stocks in June, followed by a move back
up in July, and then look for it to top
in August or September. And you might
say, "Well, why why do I keep saying
August or September?" If you look at the
last three midterm years in 2018, you
can see the S&P found a top in August.
If you look at 2018, you'll see that it
found a top in September.
And if you look at 2014, you'll see that
it topped out
um in September. So, my argument is just
simply I think we're going to see a top
in in August or September. The S&P will
then drop, and then Bitcoin will then
drop, and then that will allow the sort
of that market cycle bottom to form. And
that is my guess as to how this plays
out, but in the short term, Bitcoin is
stuck between a rock and a hard place,
and until we really break through one of
these,
it's just a it's a waiting game. It's
like 2018, right? Like in 2018
we weren't getting squeezed between the
200-week moving average at all, right?
The 200-week moving average was a lot
lower. But, the point is is the setup
was the same, right? You had a low
in February and June, just like you have
it over here. And back then, it did
eventually break down. But, it back then
it took until November to break down.
Right?
If you look at how much higher the
20-week moving average was than the
range low back then, it was about 40%
higher.
Now,
from the June low, it was only about 20%
higher. So, when I say that Bitcoin in
2026 is just a less volatile version of
2018, you can see what I mean. Like,
look at this how the lows are forming
around the same time. The high in May
formed around the same time. The low in
the summer around the same time. And
then you get your countertrend rally
again around the same time. And in 2018,
that countertrend rally persisted
through the end of July, and then we
gave everything back. And then, the
market got even more boring
for basically the rest of the year. Then
we had our big liquidity event in Q4. It
reset all the on-chain indicators. It
was the last thing to go, and then the
rest is history. Now, the biggest
counterpoint
is that a lot of the people that you
would expect to sell Bitcoin in a
capitulation low arguably never even
bought Bitcoin this past cycle because
we topped on apathy.
The difficult thing is that the only
example in history where Bitcoin did go
through this apathetic top was 2019, and
it ended on a price-based capitulation
due to the pandemic. And so, this is
kind of the first test of like, well
what if you don't I mean, I'm not
calling for a pandemic, which is why I'm
deferring to time-based capitulation.
We'll see what happens, but that's the
best example we have, and it ended with
this more of black swan event that you
couldn't really predict. But those are
my views. Again, between a rock and a
hard place for Bitcoin.
The conference
in November is set in November, so that
it's around the theoretical market cycle
bottom, give or take, right? So, I hope
to see you guys there. Make sure you
guys get your ticket. Thank you guys for
tuning in. Subscribe, and I'll see you
next time. Bye.